Friends,
朋友们
did you know that GDP can be misleading?
你知道GDP它也是可以骗人的吗
The other day, when I was researching Iran's economy,
前两天我查那个伊朗经济的时候
I wanted to see its GDP per capita.
我就想看看它的人均GDP
I saw it
我一看哎
surged in the 1980s
80 年代起来了一波
then declined
然后不行了
then rose again after 2000,
2000 年之后又大涨
then declined again.
然后又不行了
But do you think
但是你以为
this is the true GDP per capita situation in Iran?
这就是伊朗真实的人均GDP情况了吗
I searched for "GDP per capita"
我仔细一搜这个人均GDP
and found so many options.
发现有这么多选项
If I clicked on this one,
我要是点开这个哎
Iran's GDP per capita looked like this.
伊朗人均GDP就长这样了
Goodness , its peak was before the
好家伙 1970 年代伊朗革命之前
Iranian Revolution in the 1970s
就是它最高峰了
and it hasn't been higher since.
到现在都没有那时候高
If I clicked on this one,
我要是点开这个呢
it looked like this
它变成了这样
The most outrageous thing is,
最离谱的啊
if I clicked on this one
我要是点开这个
Iran's GDP per capita looked like this!
得伊朗人均GDP变成这样了
If we analyse Iran's economy according to this chart,
咱要是按照这张图分析伊朗经济
wouldn't everyone be Elon Musk
那他还不得人人都是马斯克
I'm telling you,
我跟你说啊
these are all statistics from the World Bank.
这些都是世界银行统计出来的数据
We can't guarantee
准不准
their accuracy
咱不保准
but they're definitely official.
但是他一定够官方
GDP
你说说
is arguably
GDP
the most commonly used indicator
可以说是衡量各国经济
for measuring the economy of various countries.
最最最最最常用的指标了
You might think it's just a number
你以为它就是个数
that won't lie
不会骗人
but there are so many versions
但是呢却有这么多版本
like the lions on the Lugou Bridge—
就好像卢沟桥的狮子一样
different in
大小不一
sizes and shapes.
形态各异的
The intricacies behind this are not simple.
这背后的门道可不简单
Today, let's talk about this economic indicator
咱们今天就来聊聊这个
that you think you're most familiar with
你以为你最熟悉的
but which is actually
但实际上
very misleading:
非常会骗人的经济指标
GDP
GDP
Gross Domestic Product
Gross Domestic Product
Gross
国内
Domestic
生产
Product
总值
as the name suggests,
你看名字就挺清晰的
the total market value
就是在特定时期里
of all the final goods and services
一个国家或者一个区域内
produced in a country or region
生产的所有最终产品的
over a certain period of time.
市场价值
Try to understand
你理解理解哈
there are few
这里头呢
points that are easily overlooked
其实有一些非常容易忽略的点
First,
首先呢
it's produced within a specific country or region.
它是一个国家区域内生产出来的
For example, if a Chinese person
比如说一个中国人
wholly owns a Vietnamese company with all its
他全资控股了一个越南公司
production facilities in Vietnam
这个生产厂房都在越南
whose GDP should
那它生产出来东西
the products be counted in?
应该算进谁的GDP啊
That's right,
哎没错
Vietnam's .
就是越南
Even if it's wholly owned,
就算你是全资控股
it's still counted in Vietnam's GDP
它也算越南
Of course, there's another indicator
当然还有另一个指标
called GNP
叫做GNP
Gross National Product
国民生产总值
in which
这在GNP里头
it is counted as China's GNP
它就算中国的了
Second, it must be final goods.
其次呢它得是最终产品
What does that mean?
什么意思呢
Let me give you an example.
我打个比方啊
A chicken farm
一个养鸡场
raises chickens that lay two eggs.
它养鸡下了两个鸡蛋
One is sold to me
一个呢卖给了我
and I eat it directly
我直接给吃了
That's a final product
那这个就最终产品
because I ate it,
因为我给吃了嘛
so it should be counted in GDP.
这个鸡蛋就应该算进GDP
But the other egg
但是另一个鸡蛋呢
is sold to a restaurant and
被卖到餐馆里了
made into tomatoes scrambled eggs,
被做成西红柿炒鸡蛋了
then the eggs themselves
那那个鸡蛋
shouldn't be included in GDP
就不能算进GDP里头
because they're not a final product.
因为它不是最终产品
The scrambled eggs with tomatoes,
而那盘西红柿炒鸡蛋
however, should be included in GDP
应该被算进GDP
otherwise, there would be double counting.
不然其实就会有重复统计的问题
Of course,
当然了
this isn't easy to define
这个在现实生活当中
in real life
也不太容易界定
so the accounting
所以它这个核算
is prone to problems.
也很容易出问题
But theoretically, that's how it should be.
但它理论上应该是这样
Furthermore
再有
not all production activities
就不是所有的生产活动
are included in GDP
都算在GDP里
only transactions involving payment
只有有偿交易
are counted.
才算
For example, if Wang makes a toy for his son,
你就比如说老王给他儿子做了个玩具
that doesn't count.
那就不算
But if Wang's son
如果老王的儿子
then
转头
sells that toy to Li's son next door,
把这个玩具卖给了隔壁老李的儿子
that's a transaction involving payment,
他有偿交易了
and theoretically, it should be considered
那理论上就应该算
a transaction without payment.
无偿交易
Why isn't it included in GDP?
为什么不算在GDP里呢
It still represents production,
它也生产了
It has value .
对吧它也有价值
The problem is, it's difficult to calculate
问题呢就是它没法算
because
不好算
you need a market price
因为你有个市场价
to measure the value of the product.
你才能衡量这个产品的价值
Otherwise, it's just a matter of how much you say it is.
不然那不就是你说多少是多少
For example, if
就比方说
I, Lin, make you a cup of
我小Lin给你做了一杯
secret-recipe milk tea, and
秘制奶茶
you taste it and think,
你一喝哎
Wow, it's so delicious!
太好喝了
This milk tea is worth 1million
这杯奶茶值 100 万
I say that's right,
我说没错
it's worth 1 million.
它就值 100 万
So,
那你说
how much is this cup of milk tea worth?
这杯奶茶值多少钱
Can we include this 1 million in GDP?
能把 100 万算进GDP里吗
Obviously not, right?
那显然不能对吧
First, estimating
这种无偿交易
such a free transaction is extremely difficult
第一你估算起来非常困难
second, you don't have complete records.
第二你也没有那种完整的记录
So, we simply don't include it in the statistics.
所以干脆就不统计了
Okay, I believe everyone
好我相信大家
has learned something by now.
现在应该已经都学有所成了
I'll give you a few questions to test your knowledge.
我来出几道题考考大家
Does this count
你看
towards GDP?
算不算在GDP里
I spent 500 buying a bicycle
我花了 500 块钱买辆自行车
does this count towards GDP?
算在GDP里吗
Yes
哎算
most consumer purchases
大部分消费者买的
and merchandises
大部分商品
are counted towards GDP.
都算在GDP里
But if I resell this bicycle
那我转手把这个自行车
to my neighbour,
卖给隔壁老王
does that count?
算吗
No
这就不算了
secondhand goods don't count towards GDP.
二手商品不算在GDP
So I know
所以我知道
many of you
可能很多朋友啊
really like shopping on Xianyu (a Chinese online marketplace)
特别喜欢在闲鱼上消费
practically buying everything
恨不得所有东西
secondhand there.
都在闲鱼上买二手的
Your
哎你们啊
contribution to GDP
对GDP的贡献
needs improvement
还有待增加
Okay, let's go back to the bicycle
好还是这个自行车啊
let's say I add some nice stickers and modifications
如果说我给它贴上很多漂亮的贴纸
to this bicycle
加一些改装
and resell it to my neighbour
转手5,000块钱
for 5,000 dollars.
卖给隔壁老王
Does that count?
它算吗
Because I've
因为我给这个自行车
done some extra processing
进行了一些额外的加工
and production,
额外的生产动作
the added value
那这个让自行车增值的部分
should be counted towards GDP.
就应该算在GDP里
But it's not actually that easy to define.
但它实际上不是那么好界定的
We are done about bicycles.
自行车说完了哈
Now, if I buy an imported sweater made overseas,
我现在买了一个海外生产的进口毛衣
does that count?
算吗
The production of sweaters doesn't count,
海外生产毛衣的部分不算
but some of that might involve domestic shipping and
但里头可能有一部分是国内的运输啊
platform services.
平台的服务啊
So this part does count.
这部分算
Alright, next
好下一个
Does buying stocks count?
买股票算吗
No.
哎不算
If I buy stocks at $50
那我要是50块钱买股票
and they rise to $150
涨到150
does the $100 profit count?
赚的这100算吗
No, it doesn't.
哎也不算
Stock trading is an equity transfer
股票交易它是股权转让行为
it's unrelated to production.
它跟生产没有关系
So, regardless of how much you gain
所以不管你赚了多少
or lose,
亏了多少
it doesn't count.
都不算
Similarly,
类似的
the increase in asset price from
你投资任何东西
any investment
这个资产价格变化
isn't included in GDP.
增值的部分也都不算在GDP里
Therefore, a surge in stock prices
所以说股票大涨
doesn't directly affect GDP.
其实是没法直接影响GDP的
What we generally call an impact
我们一般说影响
is indirect,
也都是间接影响
the so-called "wealth effect."
就是所谓的"财富效应"
When stocks rise,
股票一涨
everyone feels richer,
大家都觉得自己更有钱了啊
businesses feel stronger,
企业也觉得自己更有实力了
and it's easier to get loans.
更容易贷款
Everyone is more inclined to invest in production
大家都更倾向于花钱 投入生产
which actually boosts GDP.
这部分它是能实际带动GDP的
But the stock price
但股票本身
fluctuations themselves don't count.
它涨跌是不算的
So, while you see many venture capital and hedge fund bigwigs
所以说
making billions
在二级市场里头
in the secondary market,
赚个多少多少亿的
they actually
他们实际上对GDP
don't contribute much to GDP.
真没多少贡献
However, the services provided by intermediary platforms
不过呢大家在交易里头
in these transactions
这个中介平台提供的服务
are counted.
是算的
For example, stockbrokers
比如说股票券商
charge you commissions, and
收你点手续费啊
investment banks earn service fees for
投行帮公司上市
helping companies go public
赚的服务费啊
These do count.
这些算
Let's continue.
咱继续哈
Does buying a house
那买房
count?
算吗
New houses, yes, but
新房算
secondhand houses don't.
二手房不算
New houses are houses that have just been built
新房嘛就是开发商刚造出来
and produced by developers.
刚生产出来的房子
If you buy one,
你买下来呢
it's considered "residential investment,"
就算是"住宅投资"
and it's included in GDP.
这个是包括在GDP里
Secondhand houses, on the other hand,
二手房呢
represent a transfer of ownership
它其实是一个所有权的流转
somewhat like a transfer of equity.
它就有点像股权的转让了
So, regardless of whether the price goes up or down,
所以不管你涨了还是跌了
it's not counted
都不算
If you give this house a major renovation
除非你给这个房子来了一个大翻新
and suddenly increase its value,
哎让这个房子一下增值了
the increase value part does count.
增值的部分就算
A restaurant makes a plate of scrambled eggs with tomatoes,
餐厅里做了一盘西红柿炒鸡蛋
This does count
这个算
If they make it but don't sell it,
那他如果做出来了没卖出去
and keep it in inventory to sell later,
放在库存里留着下一顿接着卖
does that count?
算吗
Although it's unethical
虽然不道德
but, yes.
但是算
Theoretically
理论上
once a product is produced,
这个商品只要生产出来了
even if it's kept in inventory and doesn't sell,
就算你放在库存里没卖出去
it still counts.
它也算
What if Wang buys a bottle of medicine or something
那要是老王在黑市上买了一瓶药
on the black market
或者买了个什么东西
Does it count?
算吗
Theoretically, it should,
理论上应该算
but in practice, it's difficult
但实际很难
to include in statistics.
被统计进去
The IMF has previously calculated that
IMF之前就统计过啊
the informal sector accounts for about
中低收入国家的经济活动里头
one-third of
非正规部门的
economic activity in low- and middle-income countries.
就占了大概1/3
Of course, this doesn't necessarily have to be drugs or
当然这个不一定非得是那种毒品啊
money laundering
洗钱什么的
We made a cash transaction,
就我们俩现金交易了个东西
and it's difficult to include
你这也很难统计进去
this category in statistic
这种类别
Even in developed economies,
即使在发达经济体里
this category accounts for about 15%.
也会占到大概15%
So, these
所以这些呢
can generally only be estimated.
一般就只能估算
Get the idea?
怎么样有点感觉了吧
Let's stop with the practice questions
咱不做题了哈
We don't have that many for you.
没有那么多题给你做
Since GDP is
既然GDP它是
Gross Domestic Product
生产总值
if someone tells you that
那要是有人跟你说
GDP is the sum of everyone's income,
GDP是所有人收入的总和
is that wrong?
那是不是就不对了呢
Not at all.
哎非也
Actually, a country's
其实一个国家
total factor income
它的全要素收入
equals its GDP
就等于它的生产总值
Theoretically, they are completely equivalent.
这个在理论上是可以完全划等号
However, this income
只不过这个收入呢
includes not only wages and salaries
它不光包括大家的工资薪水
but also corporate profits
还包括企业的利润
and other miscellaneous items.
还有一些杂七杂八的东西
Broadly speaking,
那笼统来看呢
GDP can be understood as the income of the entire country.
GDP可以理解成整个国家的收入
So, if you look at a country's per capita income,
所以你要是看一个国家的人均收入
it's different
跟人均GDP
from per capita GDP.
就不一样了
Per capita income
人均收入
only includes the average income of individuals,
它就只包含了个人的平均收入
so it is generally lower than GDP per capita.
所以它一般是要比人均GDP要低的
For example, in 2024,
比如说2024年
the US GDP per capita was $85,800,
美国的人均GDP是85,800美元
while per capita income was $73,200.
而人均收入是73,200美元
These two cannot be used interchangeably.
这两个是不能混用的
Here's a little tidbit for you :
一个小知识点送给你
In short, the value of
总之一个国家
all production value in a country,
它所有生产的价值
all its income
和这个国家所有的收入
and all its expenditures
还有这个国家所有的开支
should theoretically be the same
这三个理论上应该是一样的
— all of them constitute the country's GDP.
都是这个国家的GDP
This is actually the classic
这个其实就是非常经典的
three methods of calculating GDP:
GDP的三种算法
the production approach,
生产法
the income approach
收入法
and the expenditure approach
和支出法
It's like being in a class isn't it when someone
是不是有一种上课的感觉
says, "This problem has three solutions."
说"这道题有三种解法"
This isn't to say that top students are particularly brilliant
这可不是说学霸特别厉害
and want to show off their multiple solutions;
想秀自己解法多哈
it's just that GDP
就是因为这个GDP
is very difficult to calculate.
它核算起来非常困难
Therefore, most countries
所以大部分的国家呢
use these three methods
都会用这三种方法
or two of these methods
或者是三种方法的其中的两种
cross-calculated,
去交叉核算
to ensure the accuracy of GDP.
来确保这个GDP的准确性
So, let's look at each of these methods one by one.
所以呢咱来挨个看看哈
These methods
这三种方式呢
might be a bit theoretical
可能有点理论
but after listening,
但是你听完之后
you'll have a deeper understanding of GDP.
就会对GDP产生一个更深入的理解
Let's start
我们开始
with the first method: the production method.
首先第一种生产法
GDP is the gross domestic product,
GDP它是生产总值
so this method is the most intuitive.
所以这个生产法肯定最直观
It sums up
就是把所有人
everyone's contribution towards the value of
对这个产品价值的贡献
this product
给加总
For example, a plate of scrambled egg tomatoes
比如说一盘西红柿炒鸡蛋
The restaurant
这个餐厅呢
buys tomatoes and eggs
他花1块钱买的西红柿
for $1 each,
花1块钱买的鸡蛋
the dish sells for $10 yuan.
最后这盘菜卖10块钱
The extra $8
那中间增加的这8块钱的部分
is the restaurant's contribution to GDP.
就是餐厅对GDP的贡献
The tomato
而这里边这个西红柿厂
and egg factories also contribute.
鸡蛋厂也亦有贡献
Adding up their respective added-value contributions
就把他们对应那部分增值的部分
totals $10
都加起来
is included in GDP.
一共是10块钱算进GDP
This way, the total added-value of
这样全国每个企业
every enterprise nationwide
把生产的增值的部分加总
is summed to obtain the Gross Domestic Product (GDP).
就得到了国内生产总值
Its main advantage is
它的优点呢
timeliness;
很主要的一个就是及时
the data is readily available
这个数据可以来的很快
because the entire process
因为整个这个环节
doesn't involve consumers
它不涉及到消费者
and each enterprise has
而每个企业呢
a clear division of labour
分工又很明确
so everyone can calculate
所以大家都能算出来
their own added-value.
自己增值的那部分
Often, this method is mainly used
经常要是每个季度估算的时候
when estimating quarterly figures
主要就是用这种方法
but its drawbacks are
但它的缺点呢
also obvious
也很明显
it's extremely fragmented.
就是非常的琐碎
Imagine having to
你想你得把整个经济体
isolate every single aspect
生产各个环节
of the entire economy's production process
每一项都单拎出来
and add them all up.
再把它加起来
Even a simple dish of scrambled eggs with tomatoes
明明一盘非常简单的西红柿炒鸡蛋
has to be broken down into
好家伙你得给它拆成
the restaurant portion,
餐厅的部分
the egg portion,
鸡蛋的部分
the tomato portion
西红柿的部分
and then further subdividing
那鸡蛋里头
the egg portion into
还得再分成
the chicken farm portion and
养鸡场的部分
the transportation portion.
运输的部分
In short, it 's fragmented beyond recognition
总之给拆了个稀碎
It's also easy to miss
而且它也很容易漏算
or double-count.
或者是算重
Do you know what kind of countries
你知道这种方法
or regions this method
它一般比较适合什么样的国家
is generally suitable for?
或者地区吗
Places where value-added tax is the main form of taxation,
就是以增值税为主要税收方式的地方
such as mainland China
比如说中国大陆
and many European countries.
比如说欧洲很多国家
Think about the calculation of this GDP...
你想这个GDP核算
One of the main data sources
它的主要数据来源之一
is tax and financial data
就是税收财务数据
meanwhile this value-added tax
而这个增值税
is levied on the added value,
又是根据增值的部分交税
so it is naturally very compatible with the production method.
它天生就非常符合这个生产法的算法
The second method is the income approach
好第二种方法就是收入法
which basically adds up all
大概意思就是把所有的公司
the income, surplus, and profits
个人的收入盈余
of all companies and individuals
赚的钱给加在一起
You don't need to understand the formula;
啊这个公式你不用理解啊
it's not important
不重要
Let's take the previous example
还是刚才那个例子
The restaurant earned $8 right?
刚才那个餐厅不是赚了8块钱吗
Let's say the owner gives the chef $3
比如说老板给厨子分了3块钱
and keeps $5 for himself.
自己留了5块钱
How do we calculate GDP?
那怎么算GDP呢
It's $1 from eggs,
就是鸡蛋上收入1块钱
$1 from tomatoes,
西红柿上收入1块钱
$3 from the chef,
厨子收入3块钱
$5 from the owner,
老板收入5块钱
adding up to $10
加起来10块钱
That's roughly how it works
大概这样
The result measured by this method
这个方法测量出来的结果呢
will generally be lower
通常会偏低
Do you know why ?
你知道是为什么吗
Income statistics
你想收入统计
are mainly based on tax data
主要是根据税收数据
but for the income
但这个收入吧
if you report your income, you have to pay taxes.
你报了就得交税
So many people
所以很多人
might avoid reporting
可能他收入这块
their income if possible
能不报就不报了
such as grey income,
比如说很多灰色的收入
cash income , or
现金的收入
ambiguous income
模棱两可的收入
these can't be included in the statistics.
这些那就统计不进来了
Therefore, at the macro level,
所以放到宏观层面上
the overall figure
它总体算出来那个数据
is usually underestimated .
通常会偏低
That's why many countries,
所以很多国家
like China
比如说中国
don't use this method to calculate GDP.
它压根就不会用这种方式来核算GDP
Okay, the third approach,
好第三种解法了哈
and the most common and important one
也是最常用最重要的一种
is the expenditure approach
就是支出法
As the name suggests,
这个也顾名思义
it sums up everyone's
它就是把所有人
expenditure on the final goods
购买的最终商品的支出
purchased.
给加总
In the example of scrambled eggs with tomatoes
放在刚才西红柿炒鸡蛋那个例子里头
Regardless of what happened during the production process
就是不管这中间西红柿鸡蛋
chef, boss
厨子老板
ignore everything that happen in between
这中间生产发生了什么都不管
as the final consumer ,
反正我作为最终的消费者
I paid $10 for this final product
我为这盘终端产品
scrambled eggs with tomatoes
西红柿炒鸡蛋付了 10 块钱
So, my expenditure of $10
那我支出的这 10 块钱
is counted in the GDP
就算你GDP
This is a simpler and more accurate
你看这个方法在实际测量当中
method in actual measurement.
是不是更简洁更准确
Also, since people can get tax deductions
同时你想大家在报税的时候
when filing taxes,
这个支出是可以减税
there's an incentive to report all expenditures.
大家自然有激励去把支出给报全
At the macro level,
宏观层面上呢
the statistics are more comprehensive
它统计也会更全面一些
making this expenditure method
所以这个支出法
the most widely used calculation method,
也是被应用最广泛的一种算法
used by most countries.
大部分国家都会用
And it has a very important formula:
而且啊它有一个非常重要的公式
GDP equals consumption plus investment
GDP等于消费加投资
plus government purchases plus imports and exports
加政府购买 加进出口
This formula is very important;
哎这个公式非常重要啊
you can memorise it
大家可以记一下
or at least be familiar with it,
或者至少混个脸熟
as it's quite commonly used.
还挺常用的
For example, many economic analyses
比如说很多分析经济的时候
are based on this formula,
基本上都是基于这个公式去分析
explaining why a country's GDP increased
说啊为什么哪个国家GDP涨了
because of its consumption,
因为它消费怎么怎么着
investment, and
投资怎么怎么着
government-driven growth.
政府带动了什么什么
I won't delve into the specifics of the formula,
哎具体我就不深挖这个公式了
nor do I want to be too academic,
我也不想讲太学术
but
但有一个点
I think it's necessary to clarify one point
我觉得还是有必要跟大家再明确一下
the investment mentioned here
就是这里头说的这个投资
is different from
跟我们日常生活当中理解的投资
the investment we understand in everyday life.
是两个概念
The investment we usually talk about—
我们平时说的投资
buying stocks
你买了股票
gold
买了黄金
or funds—
买了基金
is not considered investment in GDP.
这些在GDP里头都不叫投资
GDP refers to
GDP里指的是什么啊
the inputs of a typical enterprise for production.
就是一般企业它为了生产的投入
For example, if I bought a factory
比如说我买了个厂房
or a machine
我买了个电机
that's called an investment.
这种叫投资
So if someone tells you
所以要是哪天谁跟你说
one day that a large influx of funds into the stock market
最近股市有大量资金涌入
has caused GDP to rise
导致GDP上涨
you can roll your eyes
哎你可以把白眼儿直接翻到天上去
Speaking of which,
说到这有朋友肯定想问了
some of you are probably wondering
咱聊这么半天
why we haven't explained
也没解释
why those GDP per capita trends in Iran
最开始伊朗那几张人均GDP走势图
are different.
为什么不一样呀
Well, that brings us to
哎这就说到了
the various methods we just discussed
刚才咱们说的各种方法
how to measure GDP each year.
都是每年怎么去测GDP
To know GDP
那我们想知道一个GDP
you can't just get a static number
它不是想就知道一个静态的数字
because it needs to be compared
因为它横向
horizontally with different countries and
需要跟不同的国家去对比
vertically with different time periods.
纵向需要跟不同的时间去对比
This requires different adjustments
这就需要对每年GDP的数据
to the annual GDP data.
经过不同的调整
The problem lies here:
问题就出在这儿了
different adjustments
不同的调整
result in drastically different GDP trend charts.
就会得到截然不同的GDP走势图
The Iranian example we just mentioned
咱刚说伊朗那个例子
is definitely not uncommon
它绝对不是罕见
especially in developing countries.
很多尤其是发展中国家
Using different adjustment methods,
你用不同的调整方法
the resulting GDP trend charts
算出来的GDP走势图
can be completely different.
可以说是完全不一样
Let's take it step by step.
咱一步一步来
For example,
比如说伊朗
if I take the annual GDP data for Iran
如果说我把每年得到的GDP数据
without any processing
不加任何处理
2024 was 2.16 billion rials,
2024年是21.6亿里亚尔
2023 was 1.58 billion
2023年是15.8亿
plot these annual data together
这样每年的数据连起来
in a table,
绘制成一张表
it looks like this.
它就长这个样子
This is obviously unreasonable, right?
这显然不合理对吧
Where does the problem lies in?
问题出在哪呢
It's inflation
就是通货膨胀
If I want to see
那如果我想看
a country's true growth,
一个国家真实的增长情况
I need to adjust prices
你就得调整物价
to get a figure like this: if I use last year's price level,
得到一个如果我按去年的物价水平
what should this year's GDP be?
今年的GDP应该是多少
This adjustment index
哎这个调整指数
is called the GDP deflator.
就叫做GDP平减指数
It's actually similar to the inflation rate
它其实有点类似于通货膨胀率
except that inflation
只不过通货膨胀呢
measures the price changes
衡量的是消费者
of a basket of consumer goods
那一揽子产品的物价变化
while the GDP deflator
而这个GDP平减指数
measures
它衡量的是
the average price changes of the entire economy.
整个经济活动的平均物价变化
After annual price adjustments,
这样经过每年一个物价调整
we get the second chart:
这就出现了第二张图
Iran's GDP per capita at
根据本地计算的
constant prices
不变价格的
calculated locally.
伊朗人均GDP
However,
但是呢
this is calculated
这个是根据本币
in the Iranian rial
伊朗里亚尔计算的
If we want to compare different countries,
如果我想不同国家之间对比怎么办呢
the most common way
最常见的办法
is to convert everything to US dollars.
就是都转换成美元
So, if I convert Iran's annual GDP
所以说如果我把伊朗每年的GDP
into US dollars using the exchange rate of that year,
通过当年的汇率换算成美元
we get the third chart:
就得到了这第三张图
GDP per capita in current US dollars.
现价美元人均GDP
This allows Iran to be compared horizontally with other countries.
这样伊朗就可以横向跟其他国家对比
However, this chart
但是这张图
actually includes the inflation rate of the US dollar itself,
其实包含了本身美元的通货膨胀率
so after removing the inflation rate of the US dollar, we
所以我在剔除美元的通货膨胀
get the fourth chart:
就得到了第四张图
GDP per capita in constant US dollars.
不变价美元人均GDP
This unifies the exchange rates of various countries
哎这样既统一了各国的汇率
allowing for horizontal comparisons between countries,
横向上各国可以相互对比
and also unifies the comparisons between different time periods.
纵向上又统一了不同时间的物价
This is already quite good, right?
这很好了吧
But that's not all. I have another issue to tell you.
还没完我跟你说还有个问题
Even at the same time,
就即使是同一个时间同一个商品
the price of the same product in the US
这个东西在美国卖的价钱
is different from its price in
和它换算成伊朗里亚尔
Iran when converted to
在伊朗卖的价钱
Iranian rials.
它是不一样的
Generally, it's
通常情况下
cheaper in developing countries,
发展中国家会更便宜
Everyone should have
这个大家应该对吧
noticed this.
都有感觉
I don't know if you've seen similar questions
我不知道大家有没有在小红书上
on Xiaohongshu (a Chinese social media platform)
刷到过类似这种问题
What is the equivalent of
说纽约年收入20万美元
an annual income of $200,000 in New York in China?
相当于国内什么水平
Think about it, $200,000
你想啊 20万美元
is roughly equivalent to 1.4 million RMB.
大概等于140万人民币
This question is actually very broad;
这个问题其实非常宽泛了
you can think about it or argue it
你可以有无数的角度去思考
from countless angles.
或者去论证
So you see the replies below
所以你看到底下那回复
are all over the place.
五花八门
Some say it's roughly equivalent to 300,000 RMB,
有的说大概是相当于30万人民币
some say 500,000
相当于50万人民币
some say 800,000
有时候相当于80万人民币
In short, no one says it exceeds 1.4 million RMB.
总之没有人说超过140万人民币
In fact, everyone agrees on the fact
其实啊大家都默认了一个事实
that the purchasing power of $200,000 in the US
就是20万美元在美国的购买力
is definitely less than
它肯定不如换算过来
the purchasing power of 1.4 million RMB in China.
140万人民币在中国的购买力
Don't argue,
大家也别杠啊
I'm just giving a rough average purchasing power
我就是说一个大致平均的购买力
So if you want to compare
所以如果你要是想去对比
the productivity of
各个国家生产产品
products and services produced by different countries
生产服务的这个生产力
and remove the price differences between countries,
去掉各国物价之间的差异
you need to use
就需要用到
Purchasing Power Parity per capita GDP
购买力平价人均GDP
Purchasing Power Parity
Purchasing Power Parity
PPP.
简称PPP
For example, China in 2024
比如说中国2024年
GDP is $18.7 trillion,
GDP是18.7万亿美元
so if we calculate it using purchasing power parity,
那如果按购买力平价算
it's $38.2 trillion
就是38.2万亿美元了
more than double!
一下翻了一倍多
This isn't my estimate;
这不是我估算啊
it 's the World Bank's estimate
是世界银行估算
It actually exceeds the US's
它其实就超过了美国的
$29.2 trillion.
29.2万亿美元
This broadly means that,
这其实笼统的就说明啊
according to the World Bank's estimates,
根据世界银行的估算
the price of the same thing
同样的东西
in the US is
美国的价格
2.04 times that in China.
是中国的2.04倍
Returning to our initial question about Xiaohongshu, a
那回到我们最开始说小红书那个问题
New York income of $200,000 ,
纽约收入20万美元
calculated using PPP
按购买力算
is equivalent to a mainland income of $98,000
就相当于大陆收入9.8万美元
or 700,000 RMB
也就是 70 万人民币
You can answer that on Xiaohongshu.
哎你可以去小红书回答一下了
Just say it's a World Bank estimate.
你就说这是世界银行估算
Okay, let's get back to the point.
好咱说回来哈
So, if
所以说
you want to see the changes in Iran's
你要看伊朗
real per capita productivity,
真实人均生产力的变化
you'll see this fifth chart :
就会有了这第五张图
PPP GDP per capita
购买力平价人均GDP
But this hasn't adjusted for inflation yet
哎但这还没调整通货膨胀呢
After adjustment
等你调整完之后
you'll see the sixth chart :
又有了第六张图
PPP GDP per capita with constant prices.
就是购买力平价 价格不变人均GDP
I might be explaining this a bit fast,
我讲的可能比较快啊
so you might be confused after listening
估计大家听完可能都是蒙的
But that's okay.
哎不重要
In short, these six indicators
总之呢这六个指标
assess Iran's GDP per capita based on
就是分别从
whether the exchange rate is unified,
是否统一了汇率
whether purchasing power is unified,
是否统一了购买力
and whether inflation
是否统一了通货膨胀
is unified
来评估伊朗的人均GDP
If you look at it this way,
那你说要是这么看的话
then
最后这个
PPP GDP per capita with constant prices
购买力平价 价格不变人均GDP
should be the best indicator, right?
应该是最好的指标了吧
Well, not necessarily
哎其实也不一定
What is the best?
什么叫好
You see, the official statistic
你看啊从官方统计出来的
after GDP figures for the year,
当年GDP之后
all the unified conversions
所有统一的换算
have to be estimated manually
都是要经过人工估算
and calculated manually.
去计算出来的
Especially for countries like Iran,
尤其是对于像伊朗这种国家
the official exchange rate and the actual exchange rate
它官方的汇率和实际的汇率
may differ greatly.
可能就差别很大
The official inflation figures
官方统计那个通货膨胀
may not be accurate either.
也不一定准
The outside world doesn't know the price level.
它什么物价水平外界也不知道
So many adjustment factors
这么多调整因子
need to be estimated by analyst at the
都需要在千里之外的世界银行
World Bank and IMF thousands of miles away .
IMF的分析师去估算
The more conversion steps you have,
那你这中间换算的步骤越多
the larger the statistical error
统计出来的那个误差
may be,
可能就越大
especially for countries like Iran with
尤其是像伊朗这种
insufficient data
数据严重不足的国家
the accuracy is even lower.
估算的准确性就更低了
Leave alone World Bank
你别说世界银行
even Universal Bank
宇宙银行
wouldn't know
也不知道
how much is Iran's true inflation rate.
伊朗真实的通货膨胀率是多少
This is essentially the art of statistics.
这个其实就是统计学的艺术
The more perfect the indicator,
理论上越完美的指标
the more human estimation and adjustment are needed,
就需要越多人为的估算调整
and the greater the calculation error becomes.
它计算的误差反倒就越大
This is somewhat similar to the uncertainty principle in quantum mechanics
这有点像量子力学的测不准原理
when the precision is high enough,
就是当你这个精度高到一定程度
position and momentum cannot be obtained simultaneously.
位置和动量根本没法同时精确得到
However, quantum mechanics inherently
哎不过量子力学它是本生
possesses uncertainty in its physical properties,
物理属性上就存在不确定性
while GDP
而GDP呢
as a measurement,
咱就是说它是测量
cannot be precisely measured.
没法测准
Therefore
所以说啊
because of these statistical errors,
就是因为有这些统计误差
when we look at economic data
我们平时在看经济数据的时候
we usually choose a compromise.
通常会选择一个折中的方案
While there are
这么多GDP里
ideal indicators of GDP that
虽然有那种什么都调整完的
have everything adjusted,
非常理想的指标
most of the time when
但大部分时候
we talk about a country's GDP,
我们说一个国家的GDP
we are referring to its current GDP in US dollars,
说的都是它当前美元的GDP
which is the GDP of that year
就是当年的GDP
converted to US dollars using that year's exchange rate.
按照当年的汇率换算成美元
Because this data
因为这个数据
doesn't actually have as many estimations and adjustments
它其实没有那么多估算和调整
at the same time
同时呢
we can also make horizontal comparisons between different countries.
各个国家之间又可以去横向对比
Because
其实啊
of these many calculation methods
就是因为它有这么多的算法
you'll find a very interesting phenomenon
所以你会发现一个非常有意思的现象
except for the US,
就除了美国
the GDP growth rate and annual GDP of
各个国家GDP
other countries
它的增长率
don't match up.
和它每年的GDP是对不上号的
What does this mean?
什么意思呢
For example, let's look at China's GDP
比如说咱看中国的GDP
The GDP in 2024 was $18.74 trillion, and
2024年是18.74万亿美元
in 2023 it was $18.27 trillion.
2023年是18.27万亿美元
Based on this calculation,
要这么算的话
the GDP growth rate in 2024 should be 2.6%.
2024年的GDP增速应该是2.6%
However,
但实际上
China's GDP growth rate in 2024
中国2024年的GDP增长率
was actually 5.0%.
不是5.0%吗
Similarly, for example, if we look at
同样哈比如说我们看2021年
China's official GDP growth rate in 2021, it was 8.6%
中国官方GDP增长率是8.6%
But if we calculate it based on
那如果我们按刚才
the annual GDP figures we just discussed,
每年GDP算出来的话
the growth rate would be as high as
它的增速竟然高达
21.3%.
21.3%
Is there a mistake in the calculation?
你说是哪算错了吗
Actually, there isn't.
哎其实并没有
there's no mistake.
哪都没算错
Generally, when we talk about the annual GDP growth rate,
一般我们说每年GDP的增长率
we're referring to the local currency
说的是本币
that is, the real GDP growth rate calculated after
也就是说人民币剔除掉通货膨胀
adjusting for inflation in RMB.
算出来的真实GDP增长率
But if we use the GDP figures from those two years
但如果我们用这两年GDP的那个数
to calculate the growth rate
换算出来增长率
it's actually the
它其实算的是
growth rate after conversion to USD.
你换算成美元之后的增长率
It's too affected by exchange rate fluctuations
它受汇率波动影响就太大了
making it less reasonable as a
作为短期的GDP评判指标
short-term GDP indicator.
它就不太合理
But if we look at the long term,
但要是看长期
some people prefer to look at the USD.
有些人他就是喜欢看美元
It's a matter of opinion.
这个吧就仁者见仁智者见智
Anyway, after discussing so many
反正我刚才聊了这么多
different and varied GDP figures,
乱七八糟各种各样GDP
I believe you've grasped the
大概意思
general idea
我相信你应该已经明白了
that is GDP
就是GDP
is not a single
它其实并不是一个唯一的
objective standard answer
客观的标准答案
It is deceptive.
它是会骗人的
It becomes misleading
它一旦涉及到横向对比
when it comes to horizontal
涉及到纵向对比
or vertical comparisons.
它就会带有迷惑性
So
所以你啊
whenever you see GDP
但凡看到GDP
you can always ask,
其实你都可以进一步问一下哎
Which GDP are you referring to?
您指的是哪一个GDP呢
This makes you seem very professional.
这样就显得你非常的专业
Okay, we've talked about what GDP is,
好刚才咱们说了GDP是什么
how to calculate it
怎么算
how to measure it,
怎么测
and how to compare it
怎么比
Seems like we've covered everything
感觉聊挺全了
but there's still a fundamental question
但其实还有一个本质的问题
we haven't addressed
咱一直没说
why do people value GDP so much
就是大家为什么这么看重GDP
Why does it has to be GDP?
为什么就是它
Is it without problems?
它没有什么问题吗
Of course, there are
那问题肯定有
many problems.
而且多了去了
What do we generally use GDP for?
我们一般用GDP干什么
To measure a country's economic level
就是衡量一个国家它的经济水平
or to give a very general
或者非常笼统的去看看
idea of ​​its level of development.
这个国家发达程度这么个概念
But economic level
但经济水平
certainly involves more
它肯定不止生产力
than just productivity.
这么一个方面
Let me give some common limitations of GDP
我举一些常见的这个GDP的局限性
For example, it doesn't measure income inequality
比如说它不衡量贫富差距
it doesn't care about people's happiness or
它不管大家生活的幸不幸福
quality of life,
生活质量怎么样
it doesn't consider environmental damage
它也不管这个对环境的破坏有多大
and it doesn't consider sustainable development, etc.
也不管可持续发展等等
If you consider a country's economic development
如果说你把一个国家的经济发展
as a moving car,
看成一辆行驶的车
then GDP
那这个GDP
simply measures
就是简简单单衡量这个车速
how fast it's going and
它开得到底有多快
where it's headed.
具体这辆车它正在往哪开
Whether the car itself is old or
车本身有没有老化
worn out,
有没有磨损
GDP doesn't care about any of that.
GDP全都不管
Frankly, these are all
这些吧说实在的
quite straightforward,
都挺直观的
so I won't elaborate.
我就不多说
But even if
但就算哈
we only want to measure economic productivity
我们只想衡量经济的生产力
like how fast a car drives
就是想看车开得多快
GDP actually has some problems.
GDP它其实也是有一些问题的
Let's talk about this.
这个我们来说道说道
I wonder if anyone has heard of
不知道大家有没有听说过
something called the "broken windows theory."
一个叫做"破窗谬论"
In other words, a child
就是说有一个小孩
breaks a window
打破了一块玻璃
and pays someone to repair it,
然后他花钱请人把这个玻璃给修好了
the whole process
整个过程
doesn't actually improve society
对这个社会其实没有任何改进
and might even waste time or resources.
甚至还可能浪费了一些时间或者资源
However, the overall GDP is boosted
但是它总体GDP因为修窗了嘛
because the window was repaired.
GDP被拉动了
We just mentioned that GDP
我们刚才说GDP
doesn't measure the degree of environmental damage.
它不衡量对环境的破坏程度
In fact, not only does it not measure environmental damage, but
其实它不光不衡量
if the environment is damaged
如果这个环境被破坏了
or to put it more extremely,
或者说极端一点
if there's a natural disaster
如果经历了自然灾害
followed by reconstruction,
你再重建一波
this can actually boost GDP in the short term.
这个短期反而是会拉动GDP的
This clearly shows that
这个就是很明显
the GDP indicator is malfunctioning.
GDP它指标失灵了
Furthermore,
你再比如说经济当中
a purely false economic boom
单纯的虚假繁荣
can also lead to inflated GDP.
它也会导致GDP虚高
What does this mean?
什么意思啊
Let me give you an extreme example
我给你举个极端点的例子
say I build a playground
比如说我现在搞了一操场人
then I divided them into two groups, A and B.
然后把他们分成AB两组
I said, "Okay,
我就说了好
now group A will give group B a back massage
现在A组给B组捶背
Each person in group B will give group A $100
B组每个人给A组100块钱
Regardless of whether group B needed the massage, everyone
大家也不管这B组的人需不需要捶背
started massaging.
就开始捶
After that, I said, "Okay, now group B will give
捶完之后我再说了好
group A a shoulder massage.
现在B组给A揉肩
Group A will then give group B $100 and
A组再给B组100块钱
start massaging.
开始揉
See how this goes on?
你看这么折腾一通下来
In a single day, GDP
GDP一天之间
might surge by tens of thousands.
可能暴涨了好几万
This is a very typical example of false prosperity.
这就是一个非常典型的虚假繁荣
Sounds absurd, right?
听着非常扯对吧
But it does happen in real life.
但现实生活中确有其事
Companies
企业之间为了做高营收
might collude to trade,
可能就会商量好了
offering each other
相互交易
"back massages" and
哎你给我“捶背”
"shoulder massages" to increase revenue.
我给你“揉肩”
There's no profit
也没有利润
but revenue goes up,
但是营收就做上去了
and then the entire country's GDP goes up,
然后整个国家GDP也上去了
This is a very typical example of false prosperity
对吧
and GDP failure.
GDP失灵的例子
What I want to say is that
但是呢我想说的是什么
even though we know GDP is imperfect
就算我们知道GDP它是不完美的
but it is the most quantifiable
但是它是相对最可量化
and comparable indicator.
最可比较的一个指标
Adding a bunch of adjustments like happiness indices,
你要是整一堆幸福指数
environmental indices, and
环境指数
income inequality,
贫富差距的修正
they won't actually make GDP more perfect
它其实并不会让这个GDP更完美
On the contrary, it might make it easier to exploit loopholes,
反倒可能会让它更容易钻空子
becoming more corrupt and unreliable.
变得更脏更不可信
In statistics,
统计学里头
if a concept
如果某个概念
cannot be measured stably and repeatedly,
它没有办法被稳定的重复的测量
it has no practical significance at the policy level.
那它在政策层面就没有操作意义
For such large-scale statistical studies,
像这么大规模的统计
reliability is often superior to validity.
信度往往是优于效度的
GDP is already
这个GDP已经是我们可以找到的
the most reliable
可以跨时间比较
indicator of economic level that
跨地区比较的
we can find
相对最可信的
that can be compared across time and regions
衡量经济水平的一个指标了
In fact, think about other indicators
其实你想想其他指标
even the most common one like inflation, CPI
即使是我们最常见的通货膨胀CPI
it measures changes in the prices of a basket of goods.
它衡量的是一揽子商品的价格变化
But which basket of goods should be included?
那你哪揽子商品
Should oil and housing
你这石油 住房
be included
到底该不该算进去
It is a matter of debate among economists.
很多经济学家一人一个说法
Take the unemployment rate, for example.
再比如说失业率
It measures how many people are looking for work,
它要统计有多少人想找工作
and there's no universally accepted definition of
怎么叫想找工作
looking for work.
它根本没有统一的定义
Therefore, unemployment rates across countries
所以说各国的失业率
are practically impossible to compare directly
它其实根本没法去横向对比
GDP, on the other hand
你看就这个GDP
is clean, straightforward, and
干干净净清清爽爽
uncontroversial.
没有争议
This is why
这也是为什么
countries use GDP
各国都会把GDP
as the primary indicator of economic performance.
作为衡量经济的头号指标
We started by discussing GDP and the economy,
你看咱本来想聊GDP聊经济
but we've ended up talking about statistics.
结果聊着聊着变成聊统计学了
In short, you could say that
总之呢可以说
a country's GDP
一个国家的GDP
is roughly equal to its economic level
就约等于它的经济水平
Now then
哎那接下来
shouldn't you ask another question
你是不是就应该再问一个问题
Which GDP are you referring to?
您指的是哪个GDP啊